<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://vjabrayilov.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://vjabrayilov.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-08-25T18:59:02+00:00</updated><id>https://vjabrayilov.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Personal webpage of [Vahab Jabrayilov](https://github.com/vjabrayilov)</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Pushing Cloud Systems Toward Bare-Metal Performance</title><link href="https://vjabrayilov.github.io/blog/2025/nyc-systems-talk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pushing Cloud Systems Toward Bare-Metal Performance"/><published>2025-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://vjabrayilov.github.io/blog/2025/nyc-systems-talk</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://vjabrayilov.github.io/blog/2025/nyc-systems-talk/"><![CDATA[<p>I had the incredible opportunity to speak at NYC Systems about pushing cloud systems toward bare-metal performance. It was a fantastic experience sharing ideas with the systems community and discussing the challenges and opportunities in bridging the performance gap between cloud and bare-metal infrastructure.</p> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Had a great time speaking at NYC Systems today about pushing cloud systems toward bare-metal performance.<br/>Big thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/eatonphil?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@eatonphil</a> for the invite, <a href="https://twitter.com/trailofbits?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@trailofbits</a> for hosting, and the community for the engaging discussion! <a href="https://t.co/BRHgzxieXq">https://t.co/BRHgzxieXq</a></p>&mdash; Vahab Jabrayilov (@vjabrayilov7) <a href="https://twitter.com/vjabrayilov7/status/1958733254754017727?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">August 22, 2025</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script> <h2 id="the-performance-gap-challenge">The Performance Gap Challenge</h2> <p>The cloud has revolutionized how we deploy and scale applications, but it comes with inherent performance overhead. Traditional virtualization layers, network abstractions, and shared infrastructure all contribute to a performance gap when compared to bare-metal systems. This gap becomes particularly pronounced in performance-critical applications where every microsecond matters.</p> <h2 id="key-areas-of-focus">Key Areas of Focus</h2> <p>During my talk, I talked about two of the systems that we have built at Columbia.</p> <h3 id="machnet"><a href="https://github.com/microsoft/machnet">Machnet</a></h3> <p>Despite a decade of research, most high-performance userspace network stacks remain impractical for public cloud tenants developing their applications atop Virtual Machines (VMs).</p> <p>We identify two root causes:</p> <ul> <li>reliance on specialized NIC features (e.g., flow steering, deep buffers) absent in commodity cloud vNICs</li> <li>rigid execution models ill-suited to diverse application needs.</li> </ul> <p>Machnet, a high-performance and flexible userspace network stack designed for public cloud VMs, uses only a minimal set of vNIC features that any major cloud provider supports. It also relies on a microkernel architecture to enable flexible application execution.</p> <p>I talked how we evaluated Machnet across three major public clouds and on production-grade applications, including a key-value store, an HTTP server, and a state-machine replication system.</p> <p>Machnet is <a href="https://github.com/microsoft/machnet">open-source</a>!</p> <h3 id="efficient-virtual-machine-scheduling">Efficient Virtual Machine Scheduling</h3> <p>We have designed and built a highly efficient VM scheduler that operates at microsecond scale.</p> <p>While I cannot share the technical details here at this stage, since the work is currently under submission to ASPLOS, I can say that it addresses long-standing challenges in virtualization performance.</p> <p>The goal is to enable tighter control over CPU resources in environments where latency and predictability are critical. I look forward to discussing the design and results once the review process is complete.</p> <h2 id="the-future-of-cloud-performance">The Future of Cloud Performance</h2> <p>The future of cloud computing lies not just in scalability and flexibility, but also in achieving performance levels that rival or even exceed traditional bare-metal deployments. This requires a holistic approach that considers hardware, software, and system design optimizations.</p> <h2 id="acknowledgments">Acknowledgments</h2> <p>Special thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/eatonphil">Phil Eaton</a> for the invitation and <a href="https://twitter.com/trailofbits">Trail of Bits</a> for hosting this fantastic event. The NYC Systems community continues to be a vibrant forum for discussing cutting-edge systems research and engineering challenges.</p> <p>The engaging discussion that followed the talk highlighted the importance of these performance optimizations in real-world deployments and the various approaches different organizations are taking to address these challenges.</p>]]></content><author><name>Vahab Jabrayilov</name></author><category term="Talks"/><category term="Systems"/><category term="cloud-computing"/><category term="bare-metal"/><category term="performance"/><category term="systems"/><category term="nyc-systems"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reflections on my talk at NYC Systems about optimizing cloud infrastructure for maximum performance]]></summary></entry></feed>